A Guide to the Robert Lowell (1816-1891) Collection
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #7843
Robert Lowell (1816-1891) Collection 1864-1891
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
7843
15 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Deposit [1963 Dec 17] 1965 Feb 16
Item Listing
- Letters
  - Robert Lowell to Julius Hammond Ward, 1864 Jul 19; ALS, 4 p.
    [Discusses
    The New Priest in Conception Bay
    , about which Rev. Ward has written in
    The Christian Examiner
    says his brother, James Russell Lowell, did not help in the making of the character "Bangs," that he had no help from anyone, except for some deletions in the second edition which Caleb Sprague Henry suggested; says that, although in poetry, he cannot make "fun," as his brother can, he needs no help with prose; disclaims familiarity with writings to which others have likened
    The New Priest
    mentions the unsympathetic, slighting way of Charles Eliot Norton and Robert Lowell's brother, James, both with the
    North American Review
    expresses the hope of a visit to Duanesburg by Ward; discusses several characters in
    mentions Mr. Tucker, George Herbert, John Keble. ]
  - Robert Lowell to Julius Hammond Ward, 1865 Jul 4; ALS, 3 p.
    [Answers a letter from Ward concerning a visit to Duanesburg; expresses a hope that the delay in his answer will not keep Ward and the Rev. Tucker from visiting him; says that, since he is crippled from an injury, he will not be able to meet them in Albany & Susquehanna Railroad; says he is also writing to Ward's address in Ansonia, Connecticut; speaks of an upcoming trip on a steam frigate; sends compliments to Tucker and William Buell Sprague. ]
  - Robert Lowell to Julius Hammond Ward, 1865 Jul 6; ALS, 2 p.
    [Sends regrets, a duplicate having gone to William Buell Sprague, that he must leave on the frigate for a trip of three or four weeks; expresses hope that Ward's visit can be postponed.]
  - Robert Lowell to Julius Hammond Ward, 1865 Aug 12; ALS, 3 p.
    [Mentions the pleasure Ward's visit gave to the rural people near the Hudson River, and to his family; discusses enlarging the rectory; mentions Bishop Philander Chase. ]
  - Robert Lowell to Julius Hammond Ward, 1866 Jan 23; ALS, 3 p.
    [Comments on the doggerel in the
    Round Table
    asks if Ward received his hymn in the first draft; states that Thomas Hughes does the Lowell family too much honor in saying eight members died in the Civil War, three of whom ( Stephen George Perkins, Robert Gould Shaw, and one of the Russells), belong to other families; refers to an article by Thomas Hughes, "Young Heroes of the Civil War" (published as "Peace On Earth" in
    Macmillan Magazine
    , London, January 1866); article states that eight members of the Lowell family died in the Civil War.]
  - Robert Lowell to Julius Hammond Ward, 1866 Sep 19; ALS, 3 p.
    [Mentions unfulfilled hopes that Ward would visit; discusses work on enlarging the rectory; mentions Tucker's current employment and the
    Church Monthly
    . ]
  - Robert Lowell to Julius Hammond Ward, 1875 Apr 26; ALS, 2 p.
    [Expresses pleasure that Ward is moving to a parish in Marblehead, Massachusetts; praises Newfoundlanders and other British fishermen as kindly and loving; mentions reviews of
    Antony Brade, A Story of a School
    , in
    The American Church Review
    and
    Scribner's Monthly
    , and one to be in
    International Review
    hopes to visit him in Marblehead. ]
  - Robert Lowell to Julius Hammond Ward, 1878 Nov 14; ALS, 4 p.
    [Thanks him for his critique of
    A Story or Two from an Old Dutch Town
    in
    The Times
    discusses the way the American-Dutch characters in the stories were made and that the Dutch like the book; acknowledges that those who didn't like
    Antony Brade
    will not forget their unkindness and hopes other higher guides of opinion will approve; mentions William Eliot Griffis and his book
    The Mikado's Empire
    , Soloman Stoddard, Whitesuntide at Pinkster Hill in Schenectady,
    The Christian Intelligencer
    , and some fictional characters.]
  - Robert Lowell to Julius Hammond Ward, 1881 Nov 9; ALS, 3 p.
    [Expresses satisfaction with the part Ward will have in Bishop William Stevens Perry's
    The History of the American Episcopal Church, 1587-1883
    comments that a serious medical problem has kept him from intellectual work and that he has been idle except for six months in his old rector's job in Duanesburg; and offer from a publisher for a new book has had to wait; mentions Mary Ann Duane Lowell. ]
  - Robert Lowell to Julius Hammond Ward, 1887 May 20; ALS, 4 p.
    [Thanks him for his sympathy on the death of his son; discusses his son's good character; states that Ward deserves good pay for his work and asks if it would be improper, in writing to Henry Mason Baum, to say that if he still wants his articles it may be possible to arrange matters; mentions writing to Roberts Brothers requesting that Ward be sent some books.]
  - Robert Lowell to Julius Hammond Ward, 1887 May 27; ALS, 3 p.
    [States that he has not heard from Roberts Brothers and fears that they will not be able to buy a copy of
    , that Roberts Brothers holds the plates, hoping to bring out a new edition after he has given them another novel to publish; fearing that "out of print" means "out of stock," he is sending a copy of the first edition of
    and a second edition of
    Poems
    , and that Roberts Brothers can supply their later publications; discusses how he has not fulfilled others' expectation of him; mentions Levi Hedge, Frederic Henry Hedge. ]
  - Robert Lowell to Julius Hammond Ward, 1887 Jul 5; ALS, 4 p.
    [Discusses Ward's being cheated regarding a horse and offering to help find another (including a passage in Latin regarding his own experiences with horses); tells him to do as he likes about he paper for
    Critic
    discusses the style of portrait he has selected for the frontispiece, as the article will be given first place; mentions that Henry Mason Baum asked for some "points" from Edward Josiah Stearns, which Robert Lowell must now forward.]
  - Robert Lowell to Julius Hammond Ward, 1888 Mar 20; ALS, 4 p.
    [Thanking Ward for his letter of sympathy regarding his son's death; discusses the Lord's handling of the death, that overwork killed his son, and that Ward should slow down, including not writing that article on Robert Lowell, unless he's paid and it is done in lieu of other work; discusses the history of attempts to get the article, "Dr. Robert Lowell and His Writings," written; mentions a portrait; mentions Henry Mason Baum, Epephanius Wilson, Edward Josiah Stearns, Francis Alexander, Chester Harding,
  - Robert Lowell to an unidentified man, 1890 Mar 7; ALS, 4 p.
    [Expresses pleasure at hearing from him, mentions his "office and success in Glasgow" and "Mess. Phillips & Sampson's day"; includes a detailed autobiography and a list of his writing; mentions Washington Allston, Joseph Green Cogswell, George Bancroft, Levi Hedge, Frederic Henry Hedge, Wendell Phillips, Alonzo Potter, Alexander Viets Griswold, James Duane, the Rev. P. M., Benjamin Franklin Butler,
    Atlantic Monthly
    ,
    Atlantic Tales
  - Robert Lowell to Julius Hammond Ward, 1891 Aug 8; ALS, 2 p.
    [Discusses his lack of respect for "newspaper theology" and keeping up with the recent religious controversy; mentions several articles attributed to Ward; states that he was opposed to the choice of Phillips Brooks for bishop; mentions his recovery from his fourth attack of winter cholera.]